Bathing Micky
We are all born,
and eventually we all die -
我們出生，然後我們死亡
- that is how it
has all been planned.
這全部都是計畫好的。
You don't know when it will happen...
And thinking about it is of no use.
你不知道什麼時候會發生.....想這件事情也是沒意義。
To paraphrase Socrates:
套用蘇格拉底所說的話；
"If death is but a long sleep,
it must be a wonderful thing."
如果死亡只不過是一個漫長的睡眠，
它一定是一個美妙的事情。
One should never fear the unknown.
一個人不應該畏懼不知道的事物。
He was fun,
and always in a good mood.
他很風趣，總是有著好心情。
And he was very intelligent.
He would write songs and speeches...
他非常的聰明。
他會寫歌、詞.....
He was always
looking for fun and games.
他總是在開玩笑和遊戲。
And that was great,
because no one likes a curmudgeon.
那真的很棒，因為沒有人喜歡一個倔老頭。
Love is having someone
you enjoy being with...
愛就是擁有一個你喜歡和他相處在一起的人...
Someone who...
有一個....
Someone whose company you
really enjoy and who brings you joy.
一個帶給你快樂和享受他的陪伴。
Someone who is interested
in the same things as you -
一個和你有著相同的喜好
- and with whom
you enjoy your daily life.
並讓你享受你每天的生活。
I believe that to be very important.
我相信這非常的重要。
And then there is the sexual aspect.
That's usually how it all begins...
當然這其中還有著性。
通常這就是一切的開始....
When we got married
we didn't want children -
我們剛結婚時，我們並不想要小孩。
- because my husband was Jewish
and Hitler had occupied Denmark.
因為我的丈夫是猶太人，希特勒佔領了丹麥。
When I woke up on 9th April, 1940,
there was a terrible racket.
當我在1940年4月9日起床時，一個很可怕的聲響。
I went to the window and opened
the blinds to have a look -
我跑去窗戶旁打開百葉窗....
- and the sky was filled with planes,
dropping something from the air.
從滿是飛機的天空中掉了東西下來。
It was unreal.
It was like a bolt from the blue.
一點都不真實，好似晴天霹靂。
It was like a
sudden slap to the face.
就好似被打了一巴掌。
It was...
We didn't know what was happening.
我們不知道發生了什麼事。
They would transport Jews on trucks
and load them onto ships.
他們會把猶太人載上卡車，在運上船。
We didn't know how bad
the concentration camps were.
我們不知道集中營到底是怎樣。
There were rumours that, where a Jew
was married to a non-Jewish person -
有傳言，一個猶太人娶了一個非猶太人
- you would both be okay. At least
that's what the Germans said -
你們兩個可能會沒事。至少德國人是這樣說
- but no one believed them. We then
received word from a "good" German -
但沒人相信。我們接著從好德國人那得到消息
- that on a certain day in October -
在十月的某一天，
- all the Jews were
going to be rounded up.
所有的猶太人被集中起來。
I was guilty of miscegenation
because I had married a Jew.
我因為和一個猶太人結婚。
That was a term they used to
describe those who were not Aryans-
他們有一個專業名詞來描寫那些非亞利安人
- the race that they were so fond of.
他們是如此的尊敬那個種族。
It wasn't a time we enjoyed, with
the things they had against the Jews.
對猶太人來說，這段時間並不是那麼的美好。
If we had a child together...
假如我們有了孩子....
Supposedly, it was the mother who
determined it... But we thought...
據說，這是母親的決定....但我們認為....
We didn't trust the Germans, and the
child of course would be half-Jewish.
我們不相信德國人，而且我們的小孩是半個猶太人。
So we decided not to have a child.
所以我們決定不要生小孩。
That was wonderful!
真的是太棒了!
A friend of my husband,
Henrik Kraft -
我丈夫的一個朋友 - Henrik Kraft
- knew Leif B. Hendil,
the editor of Ekstra Bladet.
認識 Ekstrabladet 的編輯 Leif B. Hendil。
(Ekstra Bladet是丹麥的報紙)
They were behind the evacuation of
Jews from Snekkersten to Helsingborg.
他們在背地裡主持著將猶太人從 Snekkersten 移動到 Helsingborg。
They had completed 30 crossings.
We were due to go on the next one.
他們已經成功完成30次。我們本來是下一梯。
That really was wonderful.
那真的是很美好。
The night in question
turned into a nightmare.
出事情的那晚成了噩夢。
Suddenly, the engine cut out
and the boat started bobbing about.
突然，引擎不動了，船開始漂。
We shouted: "What is going on?"
All the men were lying on deck.
"發生了什麼事?"我們喊著。
所有人都趴在甲板上。
They told us it was
a German patrol boat -
他們告訴我們是一艘德國巡邏船，
- and to avoid them seeing us on the
radar they'd switched off the engine.
為了不被他們的雷達發現，他們必須要把引擎關掉。
After 15 minutes
we heard this sound...
15分鐘過後，我們聽到聲音...
And we knew,
we could breathe a sigh of relief.
我們知道，我們可以鬆一口氣。
We spent two years "over there".
From October 1943 till 1945.
從1943年10月到1945年，我們花了兩年時間在那邊。
We became more optimistic as
things started going against Hitler.
我們變得更加樂觀，因為局勢開始對希特勒不利。
That kept us going. We knew
it was only a question of time.
這件事情驅使著我們繼續下去。我們知道只是時間上的問題。
We got married in '32,
and for 10-15 years -
我們在1932年結婚，在結婚的10-15年間
-we tried our best
to avoid having any children.
我們試著去避免生小孩。
When we returned home in 1945 -
當我們在1945年回家時
- we decided the time had come -
我們決定時候到了，
- and our first child was born in
1946, followed by one more in 1948.
我們的第一個小孩在1946年出生，下一個在1948年。
Timer has been set to 9 seconds...
And Micky, remember to smile.
時間設定倒數九秒，還有Micky 記得要微笑。
I always look
foolish in photographs...
我相片中總是看起來笨笨的...
That's because you always
keep talking. Let's take one more.
那是因為你總是在說話。我們在拍一張。
The most difficult thing for me is
that my husband has passed away -
對我來說最困難的事是我丈夫的過世
- and so have all my
best friends from the past 50 years.
還有過去50年間所有我最好的朋友。
That is why it is
important to have a hobby -
這是為什麼要有個興趣
- because you'll meet
people younger than yourself.
因為你會遇見比你年輕的人。
I have been lucky that way, because I
have made many friends here.
我已經很幸運了，因為我在這認識了很多朋友。
My mother-in-law
was 94 when she died.
我婆婆在94歲時過世。
She'd say: "The most difficult part
is that all my friends have died -
她說過"最令人傷心的事情是所有我的朋友都過世了，
- and that I have no one
left to talk to from those days".
沒有人可以和我一起聊著那些過去的日子。"
There is no one to share
all the good memories with.
沒有人可以分享所有的美好回憶。
That's just the way it is.
事情就只是這樣。
There she is!
^I"Tres elegant"...>
她在那!
100 YEARS OLD
100歲
Getting older is a fact of life
which you cannot change -
變老是生命中一個你無法改變的事實，
- so you might as well try
to enjoy it as much as you can.
所以你不妨去試著享受看看。
Try to keep doing the
things you've always done -
嘗試繼續做你一直在做的事情
- which is what I do.
I keep participating.
這是我做的。我盡量去參與。
Keep participating in daily life
for as long as you possibly can.
只要你可以，盡量去參與你的日常生活。
I believe that is very important.
我相信這是非常重要的。